Finding Aid for Virginia Nordby papers, 1972-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Virginia Nordby papers
1972-1992
Nordby, Virginia, 1929-
93843 Aa 2
Lawyer and University of Michigan administrator with positions as director of the Office of Affirmative Action, policy advisor to the president, university freedom of information officer, associate vice-president for government relations and associate vice-president for student affairs. Series include policy coordinator/affirmative action, topical files, personal files, and photographs; include files relating to the formulation of the university's student discriminatory policy, 1988-1989, and to her work as consultant to the Michigan Women's Task Force on Rape, 1974-1980.
5.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Nordby papers were received in two accessions in 1992 and an additional accession in 1993 (Donor No. 8080 ).
The collection is open to research.
Virginia Blomer was born in Chicago, Illinois in 1929. After matriculating at Stanford University, she graduated with distinction receiving a BA in English literature in 1951. As an undergraduate she also studied American history, philosophy and French. Three years later she received a J.D. from the Stanford School of Law. During her years at Stanford, she sat on the Board of Editors of the Stanford Law Review, serving as Article and Book Review Editor during her second and third years. Between her second and third years of law school Blomer married Gordon L. Nordby.
After serving as a research assistant for a University of Michigan law professor during the 1960's, Nordby became a lecturer in the School of Law in 1973, where she developed a course on women and the law. Also at this time, she became a consultant to the Michigan Women's Task Force on Rape. In this capacity she was the principal drafter of the Michigan Criminal Sexual Conduct Act, Public Act 266, 1974.
In 1975 she became a policy advisor in the university's Office of the President, a position which she held until 1988. She also served as the university's director of Affirmative Action, beginning in 1980. Nordby was promoted to associate vice president for government relations in 1988. At the time of her appointment she was also named secretary of the University of Michigan and she began serving as the university's chief freedom of information officer. During this period she was actively involved in the formulation and implementation of the university's student code of conduct, parts of which were later declared unconstitutional. After three years in government relations, she became associate vice-president for student affairs. In 1991, Nordby was honored with induction into the Michigan Women's Hall of Fame. She retired from the university in 1993.
The Virginia Nordby Papers (1972-1992) document the professional activities of Virginia Nordby during her tenure as a University of Michigan administrator and Law School lecturer. The papers have been divided into three principal series: Policy Coordinator/Affirmative Action, Topical Files, and Professional Files.
Subjects:
Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Women's Task Force on Rape.; Nordby, Virginia.; Rape.; University of Michigan. Affirmative Action Office.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Michigan Women's Hall of Fame--1991.1991.; Nordby, Virginia.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Policy Coordinator/Affirmative Action, 1974-1990
  The Policy Coordinator/Affirmative Action series (1.7 linear feet) contains materials created and collected by and for Nordby while she served as a policy advisor to the university's administration and as director of the university's Affirmative Action program. The series is arranged in the order in which it was originally kept by Nordby and her file folder headings have been retained. Although the headings might not indicate it, most of the materials pertain to proposed changes, additions and deletions to, and clarifications of, the Regent's Bylaws.
  - University Files, 1974-1990
    - Legal Organization
      - Academic Freedom, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
      - Open Meetings Act, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - Student Records Management
        - General, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
        - Names and Addresses, 1976-1987 (Box 1)
    - Student Participation in Decision Making, 1975-1985 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action
      - Organization of Affirmative Action Office, 1976 (Box 1)
      - Appointment Process, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
      - Compliance Review, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
      - Coordinators, 1985 (Box 1)
      - Gender--University of Michigan, 1976-1988 (Box 1)
      - Legislation--State, 1977-1983 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Student Recruitment, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
    - Non-discrimination
      - AIDS, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
      - Marital Status, 1987 (Box 1)
      - Sexual Harassment--University of Michigan, 1978-1985 (Box 1)
      - Sexual Orientation, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Board of Regents
    - Organization--Regental Power/Grievances, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws
      - Printing and Distribution, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
      - Revisions
        - Procedures (Box 1)
        - Technical (Box 1)
  - University Officers
    - General, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Vice-Presidents
      - General, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
      - Academic Affairs
        - General, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Transition Plans, 1985 (Box 1)
        - Vice-Provost--Medical Affairs, 1984 (Box 1)
      - Development, 1984 (Box 1)
      - Research, 1986 (Box 1)
      - Policy Coordinator, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - University Policy-Making Bodies and Committees
    - General, 1984 (Box 1)
    - University Senate, 1975 (Box 1)
    - University Senate--Senate Assembly, 1977-1984 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - University Council, 1988 (Box 1)
    - University Committee on Privacy & Access to Information, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Schools and Colleges
    - Definition of Governing Faculty, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Role of Department Chairs, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Authority of Rackham, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Libraries
    - Research Libraries Group, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Student Access, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Centers/Institutes/Units
    - General, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Creation of, 1979-1984 (Box 1)
    - Role of Executive Committee, 1977-1982 (Box 1)
  - Personnel/Faculty/Staff
    - Personnel
      - Hiring
        - Appointment Procedure, 1978-1985 (Box 1)
        - Nepotism Policy, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Benefits--Mental Health Care Emergencies, 1985 (Box 1)
      - Retirement, 1984 (Box 1)
      - Employee Conduct, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
      - Conflicts of Interest, 1977-1984 (Box 1)
    - Faculty
      - Definitions
        - General, 1975-1986 (Box 1)
        - Lecturers, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
        - Without Tenure, 1974-1982 (Box 1)
      - Compensation--Sales to Students, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
      - Chronology of Tenure Policy, 1974-1982 (Box 1)
      - Promotion/Tenure
        - De facto, 1975 (Box 1)
        - Divided Appointments/Part-Time Appointments, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
        - General, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
        - Historical, 1976-1981 (Box 1)
        - Non-Reappointment/Termination, 1985 (Box 1)
        - Studies, 1973 (Box 1)
      - Faculty Grievance Procedure, 1984 (Box 1)
      - Absences/Leaves, 1974-1982 (Box 1)
      - Retirement
        - Furlough, 1984 (Box 1)
        - General, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - Staff
      - Research Staff, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
      - Librarians/Curators, 1981 (Box 1)
      - Professional/Administrative Staff, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Grievance and Appeals
    - General, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Faculty
      - Model Grievance Procedures, 1983-1990 (Box 2)
    - Historical
      - General, 1975-1982 (Box 2)
      - Schools' and Colleges' Procedures, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Staff, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Students, 1975-1982 (Box 2)
  - Student Affairs
    - Student Government--MSA, 1975-1991 (Box 2)
    - Health and Safety
      - General, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Alcohol and Drugs, 1986 (Box 2)
      - Health, Student Services, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Mental health, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
      - Weapons, 1977-1982 (Box 2)
    - Conduct, Nonacademic
      - University Council, 1988 (Box 2)
      - University Judicial System, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Conduct, Academic
      - Crook Case, 1984 (Box 2)
      - General, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Liability Insurance, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
    - Greek Housing, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - Organizations, Student, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Career Planning and Placement, 1976-1983 (Box 2)
  - Academic Affairs
    - Academic Programs--Overseas Programs, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Student Evaluation of Faculty, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
    - Admissions--Pre-Admission Inquiry, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Evaluation of Academic Performance/Exams, 1976-1982 (Box 2)
    - Commencement activities, 1983-1990 (Box 2)
  - Research
    - Research Subjects--Human Subjects, 1975-1986 (Box 2)
  - Business and Finance
    - Fees--Residency, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Intellectual Properties, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - External Relations
    - Foreign Students, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Military Recruitment, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Religion and the University, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Legal Affairs
    - Defense and Indemnification, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Physical Plant
    - Buildings--Honorary Names, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Pets in Buildings, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Soliciting on Campus, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Information, Access to, 1975-1982 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The second series, Topical Files (2.3 linear feet), is particularly rich and is arranged alphabetically. Included among the files is significant documentation of the university's student discriminatory policy, the so-called "Code of Conduct." There is a complete set of drafts of the policy as well as comments and background material. There is also a large volume of material that relates to the university's policies on program review and discontinuance, which document Nordby's concern for the insurance of due process during reviews of programs and schools. Of interest are those files relating to policy issues impacting on athletics and the enforcement of Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972. Additional files address the implementation of the University's Discriminatory Harassment Policy.
  - Board of Regents
    - General Bylaw Revisions
      - Regent's Appointments, 1975 (Box 2)
      - Title Definitions, 1974-1981 (Box 2)
    - Specific Bylaw Revisions
      - R5.01--Definitions, 1976-1976; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - R5.17--Sick Leave, 1975 (Box 2)
      - R5.23--Clinical Appointments, 1975 (Box 2)
      - R6.02--Dept.of Physical Education, 1984 (Box 2)
      - R7.01--Committee on Communications, 1973-1978 (Box 2)
  - Faculty/Staff Discriminatory Policy
    - Comments, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Policy Drafts
      - 1-13, January-April 1988 (Box 2)
      - 14-24, April-May, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Drafts, April-October 1988 (Box 2)
  - Jonathan Marwil Case
    - General, 1977-1980; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - File Nos. 1-2, 1979-1980; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Part-Time Tenure Study, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
  - Program Discontinuance
    - General, 1977-1985; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Effects on Students, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Program Review
      - General, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - Appointments and Promotions, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Program Transfers, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Programs
      - CEW, 1982 (Box 3)
      - Family Practice, 1984 (Box 3)
      - Geography, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
      - Library Science, 1984 (Box 3)
      - Medical School--Guidelines, 1980 (Box 3)
      - Medical Technology, 1984 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous Programs, circa 1976-1979 (Box 3)
      - Natural Resources, 1986 (Box 3)
      - Physical Therapy, 1981 (Box 3)
      - School of Education, 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Engineering, Humanities Dept., 1982-1984 (Box 3)
      - Speech and Hearing, 1977-1987 (Box 3)
    - Programs--Defined, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Report of the Task Force on Faculty Grievance Procedures, February 1983 (Box 3)
    - Tenured Faculty, 1981-1984 (Box 3)
  - Senate Advisory Review Committee, 1975-1980; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Student Discriminatory Policy
    - General (1-2), 1988 (Box 3)
    - ACLU Lawsuit
      - General, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Background, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Printed Material, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Answers to Most Frequently Asked Questions, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Brochure--Comments and Notes, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Comments, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Complaints, Comments and Resolutions, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - Drafts
      - 1-11, 1988 (Box 4)
      - 12-Final, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Formal Mechanisms
      - General, 1989 (Box 4)
      - Drafts, 1988 (Box 4)
      - Revisions, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Housing, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Research, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Training, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Working, Miscellaneous, 1984-1988 (Box 4)
  - University Council, 1988-1989
    - General, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Notebook (Box 4)
  - Athletics
    - Big Ten
      - General, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      - Evaluation Committee Correspondence, 1984-1985; 1990 (Box 4)
    - Intercollegiate Athletics
      - General, 1986-1989 (Box 4)
      - Johnson Committee Report, 1987 (Box 4)
      - NCAA Self-Study, 1989 (Box 4)
      - Review
        - General, 1987 (Box 4)
        - Background Materials, 1985 (Box 4)
      - Women's Coaches Issues, 1986-1988 (Box 4)
    - Title IX
      - General, 1980-1988 (Box 4)
      - Lambda Kappa Sigma, 1988 (Box 4)
      - Other Institutions, 1980-1982 (Box 4)
      - Pre-Admissions Inquiries, 1981-1986 (Box 4)
  - Discriminatory Harassment Policy
    - DIPIT Implementation Plan, 1988 (Box 4)
    - DIPIT Master Plan, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Labor and Industrial Relations, Institute
    - Policy Documents, 1983 (Box 5)
- Professional Files
  The Professional Files series (1.5 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, contains materials from Nordby's activity as a member of the Michigan Women's Commission as well as files derived from her research undertaken during the drafting of what would become Michigan Criminal Sexual Conduct Act.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Photographic portraits and Snapshots, b&w and color positives (Box 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1978-1990 (Box 5)
  - American Council on Education
    - Correspondence, 1976-1988 (Box 5)
    - National Identification Program, 1986-1990; 3 folders
      - Retreat, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Self Regulation Guidelines
      - Athletics Policy Statements, 1982 (Box 5)
      - Confidentiality of Faculty Files, 1979-1982 (Box 5)
      - Financial Aid/Program Toward Degree, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - Class Materials/Guest Lecturer, 1984-1989 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Women's Commission
    - Gender Based Laws, 1979-1982; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Michigan Women's Task Force on Rape, 1974-1980 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Pay Equity Network, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Sarah Goddard Power Award, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Rape
    (primarily relating to research underlying the Michigan Criminal Sexual Conduct Act)
    - Australian Trip, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Rape Reform, 1974-1979; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Requests for information, etc. (Box 5)
    - Research
      - Consent and Resistance, circa 1974 (Box 5)
      - Evidence Against Charge, 1974 (Box 5)
      - Evidentiary Rule
        - Memoranda, 1974 (Box 5)
        - Michigan Cases, circa 1974 (Box 5)
      - Husband and Wife Rape, circa 1974 (Box 5)
      - Jury Instructions in Rape Trials, 1974 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      - Prosecuting Attorneys, 1974 (Box 5)
      - Research Papers, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
      - Statutory Rape, circa 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Writings (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1975-1982 (Box 6)
    - 1983-1986 (Box 6)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 6)
  - Wife Assault, 1976-1978 (Box 6)
  - Women and the Law (Law 794) (Box 6)